Hello, welcome everybody. How is everybody doing today? This is going to be an
مرحباً، أهلاً بالجميع. كيف حالكم جميعاً اليوم؟ سيكون هذا درساً
awesome listening and speaking class. I'm so glad that all of you are here. Welcome
رائعاً في الاستماع والتحدث. أنا سعيد جداً بحضوركم جميعاً. أهلاً
everybody. Like training a muscle. The brain is not a muscle but we build
بالجميع. الأمر أشبه بتدريب العضلات. الدماغ ليس عضلة ولكننا نبني
connections. We build stronger connections and so our aim today is for your
روابط. نبني روابط أقوى، لذا هدفنا اليوم هو أن تحاولوا
answers to try to be natural, fluent and clear. You might notice that I'm
أن تكون إجاباتكم طبيعية وسلسة وواضحة. قد تلاحظون أنني أكتب
typing as you speak. Try to look at some of these corrections that I'm making
بينما تتحدثون. حاولوا النظر إلى بعض هذه التصحيحات التي أقوم بها،
some of them are just rephrasing of what you could say maybe a little bit
بعضها مجرد إعادة صياغة لما يمكنكم قوله بشكل أفضل قليلاً.
better. It improve your fluency. But I don't want it to interrupt your speaking.
هذا سيحسن طلاقتكم. لكني لا أريد أن يقاطع ذلك حديثكم.
Just try to focus on being natural, fluent and clear. The whole goal is to
فقط حاولوا التركيز على أن تكونوا طبيعيين وسلسين وواضحين. الهدف كله هو
understand and be understood. Here's a question. What's one thing you already feel
أن تَفهَموا وأن تُفهَموا. إليكم سؤال. ما هو الشيء الوحيد الذي تشعرون بالرضا
good about when speaking English? I don't know. That's a hard one. Okay, so I
تجاهه بالفعل عند تحدثكم باللغة الإنجليزية؟ لا أعرف. هذا سؤال صعب. حسناً، أعتقد
think it's like now when I speak English, I don't feel like embarrassed if
الأمر كالتالي، الآن عندما أتحدث الإنجليزية، لا أشعر بالحرج إذا
something somebody correct me. So I think that's what something I feel good
صحح لي أحدهم شيئاً ما. لذا أعتقد أن هذا هو الشيء الذي أشعر بالرضا تجاهه الآن.
now. That comes with experience really. That does help. And the next one, what's
هذا يأتي مع الخبرة حقاً. هذا يساعد فعلاً. والسؤال التالي، ما هو
one area you think might be challenging in an English interview and why? I think
المجال الذي تعتقد أنه قد يكون صعباً في مقابلة باللغة الإنجليزية ولماذا؟ أعتقد
it will be like the new vocabulary and (I) have to express or like as you mentioned
أنه سيكون مثل المفردات الجديدة و(أنا) يجب أن أعبر أو كما ذكرتَ حضرتك،
trying to put what I'm thinking in something like a more clear and in short.
محاولة التعبير عمّا أفكر فيه بوضوح وإيجاز.
*In size. Yes. Okay. And trying to say something clearly and concisely.
بإيجاز. نعم. حسناً. ومحاولة قول شيء بوضوح وإيجاز.
All right. I agree. All of these things can be improved too the more you do it. So we
حسناً. أتفق معك. كل هذه الأشياء يمكن تحسينها أيضاً كلما مارستها أكثر. لذا يمكننا
could try to improve how we say things to make them more clear or concise in
أن نحاول تحسين طريقة قولنا للأشياء لنجعلها أكثر وضوحاً أو إيجازاً في
today's lesson. One of the most popular interview questions that they ask is
درس اليوم. أحد أشهر أسئلة المقابلات التي يطرحونها هو
tell me about yourself. They want you to open up. They want you to break the ice.
"حدثني عن نفسك". يريدونك أن تنفتح. يريدونك أن تكسر الحاجز.
They've asked this question a million times. Some people use this in order to
لقد طرحوا هذا السؤال مليون مرة. بعض الناس يستخدمون هذا من أجل
impress the other person or like I said, break the ice. What do they really want?
إبهار الشخص الآخر أو كما قلت، لكسر الحاجز. ماذا يريدون حقاً؟
What they really want is something brief, right? One to two minutes. A relevant
ما يريدونه حقاً هو شيء موجز، أليس كذلك؟ من دقيقة إلى دقيقتين. ملخص
summary of your professional background, your skills, career goals, these
ذي صلة بخلفيتك المهنية، مهاراتك، أهدافك المهنية، هذه
essential things that they need to know. Why? Because if this is the first question,
الأشياء الأساسية التي يحتاجون لمعرفتها. لماذا؟ لأنه إذا كان هذا هو السؤال الأول،
they need to have a very good one, a very strong positive first impression of
فهم بحاجة إلى تكوين انطباع أول جيد جداً، قوي وإيجابي للغاية عنك
you for that first question they ask. Here's an activity for your dream job. What
من خلال هذا السؤال الأول الذي يطرحونه. إليكم نشاط لوظيفة أحلامكم. ما هي
are one to two key achievements or skills you'd highlight and your tell me about
الإنجازات أو المهارات الرئيسية (من واحدة إلى اثنتين) التي ستسلطون الضوء عليها في إجابتكم على سؤال "حدثني عن
yourself answer. What are two skills or achievements you would highlight? I think it
نفسك"؟ ما هما المهارتان أو الإنجازان اللذان ستسلط الضوء عليهما؟ أعتقد
will be something related with decision making. And I think the other one will be
أنه سيكون شيئاً متعلقاً باتخاذ القرارات. وأعتقد أن الآخر سيكون
with like, I don't know how to say it's like when you learn something by
بخصوص، لا أعرف كيف أقول ذلك، مثل عندما تتعلم شيئاً بنفسك.
yourself. So one skill is that you are good at making decisions and that you
إذاً مهارة واحدة هي أنك جيد في اتخاذ القرارات وأنك...
and the other one is that you know a lot about yourself. The other one is like if
والأخرى هي أنك تعرف الكثير عن نفسك. الأخرى هي مثلاً إذا
I don't if I don't know something, I look for it until I know it. Okay. And I
كنت لا أعرف شيئاً، أبحث عنه حتى أعرفه. حسناً. وأنا
learn, I try to learn by myself before I on your own. Right, so learn on my
أحاول أن أتعلم بنفسي قبل أن... بنفسي. نعم، أي أتعلم بنفسي قبل أن أطلب المساعدة.
own before I asked for help. So you consider yourself to be an autonomous
أتعلم بنفسي. إذاً أنت تعتبر نفسك شخصاً مستقلاً.
person. You're capable of working alone autonomously. Is that right? Yes, I can
قادراً على العمل بمفردك بشكل مستقل. هل هذا صحيح؟ نعم، أستطيع
work both, but yeah, I try to look first by myself. And I think this would
العمل بكلتا الطريقتين، ولكن نعم، أحاول أن أبحث أولاً بنفسي. وأعتقد أن هذا
highlight the fact that you are capable of making good decisions that they're
سيسلط الضوء على حقيقة أنك قادر على اتخاذ قرارات جيدة، وأنهم لن يضطروا
not going to have to micromanage what you do that you trust that you can find
إلى الإشراف الدقيق على كل صغيرة وكبيرة فيما تفعله، وأنهم يثقون بأنك تستطيع إيجاد الإجابة الصحيحة،
the correct answer that you're not going to be a burden on them and that you
وأنك لن تكون عبئاً عليهم، وأنك تمتلك المهارات اللازمة. أعتقد أن هذه طريقة جيدة
have the necessary skills. I think that's a good way to make a good first
لترك انطباع أول جيد.
impression. Yeah, yes. So we have some different phrases that we can use to answer
نعم، نعم. إذاً لدينا بعض العبارات المختلفة التي يمكننا استخدامها للإجابة على هذا السؤال.
this question. For example, if I were to tell someone about myself, I'd say my
على سبيل المثال، إذا أردت أن أتحدث عن نفسي لشخص ما، سأقول اسمي ديفيد براون.
name is David Brown. I'm passionate about teaching English as a second
أنا شغوف بتدريس اللغة الإنجليزية كلغة ثانية.
language. I've had about 24,000 sessions online with students from all around
لقد أجريت حوالي 24,000 حصة دراسية عبر الإنترنت مع طلاب من جميع أنحاء العالم.
the world. I have taught younger students in middle school and high school
لقد درّست طلاباً أصغر سناً في المرحلتين الإعدادية والثانوية،
really identify with the work that I do in my free time. I think about it as
وأجد نفسي حقاً في العمل الذي أقوم به. في وقت فراغي، أفكر فيه أيضاً.
well. I like to spend time with my family and friends and dream about new
أحب قضاء الوقت مع عائلتي وأصدقائي وأحلم بالتكنولوجيا
technology. I don't know. That's what I might have a job interview in a
الجديدة. لا أعرف. هذا ما قد أقوله إذا كانت لدي مقابلة عمل قريباً.
little bit. Norma, tell me, do you think that would make a good first impression?
نورما (Nūrmā)، أخبريني، هل تعتقدين أن ذلك سيترك انطباعاً أول جيداً؟
Yes. Oh, I hope so. I don't know if this lesson is better for me or for you
نعم. أوه، أتمنى ذلك. لا أعرف ما إذا كان هذا الدرس أفضل لي أم لك
actually. Thank you. Thank you. Norma, this lesson is free. All right, so what made
في الواقع. شكراً لك. شكراً. نورما، هذا الدرس مجاني. حسناً، إذاً ما الذي جعل
that example easy to understand? I think I spoke a little bit too fast, but what
ذلك المثال سهل الفهم؟ أعتقد أنني تحدثت بسرعة قليلاً، ولكن ما
do you think? What made that example easy to understand? No, actually, what I
رأيك؟ ما الذي جعل ذلك المثال سهل الفهم؟ لا، في الواقع، ما
like listen (heard) was about the time that you have the experience that you have.
سمعته كان عن الخبرة التي لديك.
And also I can see like with the range of age that you can work. So
وأيضاً يمكنني أن أرى مدى الفئات العمرية التي يمكنك العمل معها. لذا
I know that you can do it with older or younger. And also that you are somebody
أعرف أنك تستطيع العمل مع الأكبر سناً أو الأصغر سناً. وأيضاً أنك شخص
that takes care of our family. Okay, also, yeah, you have some good listening
يهتم بعائلته. حسناً، أيضاً، نعم، لديك بالفعل مهارات استماع جيدة.
skills already. What I, instead of saying what I listen*, you could say what I, what
أنا، بدلاً من قول "ما أستمع إليه*"، يمكنك القول "ما، ما سمعته" بالأحرى،
I heard rather, you could say what I heard was about the experience that you
يمكنك القول "ما سمعته كان عن الخبرة التي لديك
have and also see the age ranges you can work for. So I know you can work with
وأيضاً أرى الفئات العمرية التي يمكنك العمل معها. لذا أعرف أنك تستطيع العمل مع
younger or older people. I understood you perfectly. All right, so we also have
الأشخاص الأصغر سناً أو الأكبر سناً." لقد فهمتك تماماً. حسناً، إذاً لدينا أيضاً
this other really big question. It's always asked when you're asked what are
هذا السؤال الآخر المهم جداً. يُطرح دائماً عندما تُسأل "ما هي نقاط قوتك؟"
your strengths? We have a chance to shine. We can show other people what we've
لدينا فرصة للتألق. يمكننا أن نظهر للآخرين ما لدينا.
got. What are your strengths, Norma? So you can, but what, but it's going to be
ما هي نقاط قوتك يا نورما؟ إذاً يمكنك، ولكن ماذا، ولكن يجب أن يكون الأمر محدداً بشأن هذا، أليس كذلك؟
specific about this, right? Because we can, we can tell someone that we are good
لأننا يمكننا، يمكننا أن نقول لشخص ما إننا مستمعون جيدون،
listener, but when were you a good listener? And what situation can you be more
ولكن متى كنت مستمعاً جيداً؟ وفي أي موقف يمكنك أن تكون أكثر تحديداً؟
specific? This can really help. If you can demonstrate specific, specific
هذا يمكن أن يساعد حقاً. إذا كان بإمكانك تقديم أمثلة محددة، محددة.
examples. And then when you're asked, what is your greatest weakness? You can
ثم عندما تُسأل، "ما هي أكبر نقطة ضعف لديك؟" يمكنك
choose a real minor weakness you're actively improving. So this shows that
اختيار نقطة ضعف حقيقية بسيطة تعمل على تحسينها بفعالية. هذا يظهر أنك
you're honest. And they say that you should avoid cliche is like, I'm a
صادق. ويقولون إنه يجب عليك تجنب العبارات المبتذلة مثل، "أنا شخص يسعى للكمال"،
perfectionist, unless you can generally back it up. Are you really a perfectionist?
ما لم تتمكن من دعم ذلك بالأدلة بشكل عام. هل أنت حقاً شخص يسعى للكمال؟